We have made a conscious effort to align
our definition of our territory and our
maritime zones with what international
law permits and recognises.
This has been inscribed in Article one
of our Constitution.
A Senator I was proud to co-sponsor our
archipelagic baselines law, which
defines the basis of our maritime
jurisdictions.
As President, I look forward to signing
our Maritime Zones law, which will
clarify the geographic extent of our
maritime domain.
Our efforts stand in stark contrast to
assertive actions that aim to propagate
excessive and baseless claims through
force intimidation and deception in the
West Philippine Sea.
We are on the front lines of efforts to
assert the integrity of the interests of
the constitution of the oceans.
We have defined our territory and
maritime zones in a manner befitting a
responsible and law abiding member of
the international community.
We have submitted our assertions to
rigorous legal scrutiny by the world's
leading jurists.
So the lies that we draw in our waters
are not derived from just our
imagination, but from international law.
We have on our side the 1982 laws and
the binding 2006 arbitral award, which
affirms what is ours by legal right.
In our in this solid footing and through
our clear moral ascendancy, we find the
strength to do whatever it takes to
protect our sovereign home to the last
square inch, to the last square
millimeter, the life giving waters of
the West Philippine Sea flow in the
blood of every Filipino.
We cannot allow anyone to detach it from
the totality of the maritime domain that
renders our nation whole.
As president, I have sworn to this
solemn commitment from the very first
day that I took office.
I do not intend to yield.
Filipinos do not yield.
Ladies and gentlemen, we are not only
unyielding in protecting our patrimony,
our rights and our dignity as a proud
and as a free country.
We are also firm in our commitment to
regional and global peace.
We renew this commitment at this
turbulent juncture of our history.
I repeat what I said at the United
Nations almost two years ago Amidst
challenging global tides and important
ballast stabilizes our common vessel,
our open, inclusive and rules based
international order is governed by
international law and informed by the
principles of equity and of justice.